

Vitoria-Gasteiz (Alava) - Spain



Personal Website: <a href="https://davidsantamaria.me/">https://davidsantamaria.me/</a>

Linkedin Profile: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/davidsantamaria/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/davidsantamaria/</a>

(0034)660053476



### **RESUME OBJECTIVE**

### **Senior Engineering Manager - Senior Software Engineer**

Senior Engineering Manager with 10+ years of experience managing individuals who enjoy helping out teams and individuals succeed. Supporting and growing the individuals that work surrounding me. I value and encourage teamwork, a continuous improvement mindset, delivering value to customers, commitment, empowerment, and humility.

I have comprehensive experience in leading and working with engineering teams in the architecture, specification, and implementation of complex, highly scalable, and performant systems.

I am a Software engineer interested in software analysis, architecture, and development. The Web has been my focus. I love to build things with quality, from the conception to the deployment. I take the software that I write very seriously while having an extreme passion for being the best I can be at doing what I love to do.

### **EXPERIENCE**

### Cloudbeds, Remote, Spain — Sr Engineering Manager

OCT 2020 - PRESENT

Tech Stack: Java, VueJS, Amazon AWS.

**Role:** Senior Engineering Manager at Cloudbeds. Working on the distribution vertical, leading the Distributed Systems team and the Channel manager team.

- Lead two teams of 9 software engineers, the distribution systems team in charge of making systems scalable, driving the engineering team into the microservices architecture; and the channel manager team distributing our inventory along +300 online booking channels.
- Responsibilities include technical product definition and mid-term/long-term vision, technological leadership, delivery and team growth, team health, and individuals progression.
- Partner with the leadership to create the engineering department's career path and drive the engineering team's calibration.

#### Shipped:

- Drive the technology transformation into microservices.
- Along that time, the channel manager team was able to attain a premier partnership with Booking.com.
- Partner with Google to be part of the Google Hotel Search pilot.



### Cabify, Remote, Spain — Sr Engineering Manager

APR 2019 - OCT 2020 (1 Year 6 Months)

**Tech Stack:** Golang, Redis, MySQL, NSQ, gRPC, Google Cloud Platform. **Role:** Senior Engineering manager at Cabify. Working on the Match team.

• Lead the creation of the Maps & Routes team.

### **SKILLS**

### **Interpersonal Skills**

Mentoring, Coaching, Driving Technical Decisions

### **Industry Knowledge**

Scalability, Resilience,
Observability, Software
Architecture, Good
Engineering Practices,
Software Development
Life Cycle (SDLC), Web
Applications, Web
Security, Test Driven
Development (TDD), Agile
Methodologies

### **Tools & Technologies**

Go, Java, Groovy, Grails, Spring, Spring boot, Python, Django, Kotlin, Redis, ElasticSearch, Git, SQL, Amazon Web Services (AWS), Google Cloud Platform, Unix Systems.

- Lead a group of 7 software engineers collaborating with product and data science to improve our marketplace.
- Responsibilities include technical product definition and long-term/mid-term vision, technological leadership, team growth, team health, and individuals progression.

**Shipped:** We were in charge of the matcher, **matching thousands of riders and drivers per matching round**.

- Lead the **creation of the Maps & Routes squad** responsible for **delivering the tools for providing routes and ETAs solutions for Cabify**.
- That team reduced the operational cost of Cabify on other map services by more than a half in less than one year. By that time, the operating cost of mapping services was one of the company's highest expenses.
- Ship a tool to replace Google maps on calculations of ETAs based on a machine learning model that predicts ETAs. Later we extend that tool to replace Google Maps on routes calculation.

# ebay eBay, Remote, Spain — Sr Engineering Manager APR 2016 - APR 2019 (3 Years)

**Tech Stack:** Java, Spring Boot, Kotlin, Oracle, Kafka, Google Cloud Platform. **Role:** Tech Lead at Stubhub(an eBay company) **worked on several teams across the company**, like Delivery & Fulfillment, international, Buyer Experience, and Financial Services.

- Leading multiple teams of 10+ software engineers collaborating with product, design, and business to deliver delightful user experiences.
- Responsibilities for this role include product definition and vision, technical leadership, and team management.

### Shipped:

- Lead the transformation of multiple services into Cloud Native Services.
- Drive the monolith extraction into microservices and bringing them into the cloud.

### Other achievements:

- Member of the **SDLC Committee** of the company.
- Organizer of the **Engineering culture team** inside Stubhub.

### Ticketbis, Bilbao, Spain — VP of Engineering NOV 2009 - APR 2016 (6 Years 6 Months)

Tech Stack: Java, Groovy, Grails, Spring Boot MySQL, Redis, RabbitMQ.

**Role:** Worked as a VP of Engineering at Ticketbis. I join to the company in their early days (employee #2).

- Lead the engineering group from its creation until we got acquired by eBay. By that time, the engineering group was more than 40 individuals in a technology group of over 80.
- **Build the hiring process** from the beginning acting as Hiring manager for most of our incorporations.
- Drive the growth of the engineering department and its structure.
- Our main challenges involve scalability, reliability, and real-time processing.

#### Shipped:

- Build the platform of Ticketbis at the beginning.
- Lead the growth of the department.
- Provide the long-term roadmap for the department.

### **CERTIFICATIONS**

### How to Manage a Remote Team

Coursera 2020

### **Getting Started with Go**

Coursera 2019

### Functions, Methods, and Interfaces in Go

Coursera 2019

### **Concurrency in Go**

Coursera 2019

### **Ruby on Rails**

Coursera 2016

## **Sun Certified Programmer for the Java Platform 5.0**

Sun Microsystems 2009

### Google Analytics Individual Qualification

Google 2011

### **LANGUAGES**

English, Spanish

**Universidad de Deusto, Bilbao**— Associate Professor

DEC 2012 - JAN 2013 (2 Months)

**AOL**, Dublin, Ireland — Senior Software Engineer

MAR 2008 - OCT 2009 (1 Year 6 Months)

In1Solutions, Dublin, Ireland — Software Engineer OCT 2007 - MAR 2008 (6 Months)

Irontec, Bilbao, Spain — Software Engineer

SEP 2006 - SEP 2007 (1 Year)

### **EDUCATION**

**Universidad de Deusto, Bilbao, Spain — Computer Science** SEP 2002 - JUN 2007

### SIDE PROJECTS



<u>https://curatedli.st/</u> — Collaborative Curated Content MAR 2020 - PRESENT



http://concierger.ie/ — Hotel Management 2015 - PRESENT